<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spiritual looking-glass wherein is briefly discoursed the excellency and the necessity of saving faith and likewise how it may be known whether we have this faith or no : being the substance of two sermons / preached in London July the 23, 1671 by Sam. Pack.</title>
            <author>Pack, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11242782</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11242782</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54354)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1447:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spiritual looking-glass wherein is briefly discoursed the excellency and the necessity of saving faith and likewise how it may be known whether we have this faith or no : being the substance of two sermons / preached in London July the 23, 1671 by Sam. Pack.</title>
                  <author>Pack, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47061:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Spiritual LOOKING-GLASS, Wherein Is briefly diſcourſed the Excellency, and the neceſſity of ſaving FAITH. AND Likewiſe how it may be known, whether we have this FAITH, or no. BEING The Subſtance of two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Publiſhed in <hi>London, July</hi> the 23. 1671.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Sam. Pack,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:47061:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47061:2"/>
            <head>A Spiritual Looking-glaſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 16. V. 31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And they ſaid, believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter we have a conſpicuous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of that enmity that is in the Devil, that evil one againſt God, the fountain of goodneſs. We ſee in this Chapter, that no ſooner had the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that Prince of peace, ſent <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> thoſe Sons of Peace, to Preach unto the World the Goſpel of peace, in order to the bringing in of poor Souls to the God of peace; but preſently the Devil ſhewed his enmity againſt mod by endeavouring to ſtop the courſe of the moſpel, and thereby to hinder Souls from coming to Jeſus Chriſt. The Prince of Darkneſs that rules in the hearts of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47061:3"/>the Children of darkneſs, did no ſooner ſee that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord Jeſus Chriſt had by his Servant <hi>Paul,</hi> caſt the Devil of ſooth-ſaying out of a Maid, but preſently be ſhews his enmity in filling the heart of her Maſter with a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſpirit, being uſhered in by an inordinate love to the World, and this we ſee in the 19. <hi>verſ. And when her Maſters ſaw the hope of their gains was gone, that caught</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, <hi>and drew them into the Market place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Rulers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This poor Maids Maſters, inſtead of being thankful to God that bad gained the Soul of a poor Maid, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t did practice, unlawful arts, he was inraged, becauſe that their temporal, earthly gain was gone: I do verily th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nk that tis one of the ſureſt peices of Armour that the Devil hath (even this inordinate love to the World) for the defence of his own Kingdom; when the Devil ſees that no courſe will ſerve to keep ſouls at a diſtance from Chriſt, then he betakes himſelf to this w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apon, the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate love to the world, and that doth ſeldom or never, fail him; and this we may ſee in <hi>Demus; Demus</hi> he made a large profeſſion of Chriſt, as you may ſee in the Epiſtle to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon,</hi> 24. <hi>v:</hi> and yet you ſee the Devil over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him with this approved peice of armour, inord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nate love the world, ancl did thereby
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47061:3"/>bring him to Apoſtacy;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</note> well we ſee how far the Devil did prevail, not only to ſet this poor Maids Maſters in a rage, but alſo to ſet the Rulers in a rage likewiſe; nay, he prevailed ſo far, that they were ſcourged, and they were thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon, and caſt into very great afflictions, and had their feet made faſt in the ſtocks: new, one would have thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht, that it was high time for the Devil to get into his Chariot of Tryumph; now, one would have thought, that the enemy having ſuch advantage, and thoſe ſervants of God ſuch diſacvantage as they had, that now the Goſpel would have been ſtopped in that place, and that the Devil ſhould have loſt no more of his Subjects; for my Friends, if you look in 1 he beginning of the Chapter, you ſhall ſee in the 9th. <hi>verſ.</hi> there appeared to <hi>Paul</hi> a Viſion, for to go o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to <hi>Macedonia;</hi> without queſtion this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw, was a great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him, to go to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>edonia;</hi> and now when he was come there, as ſoon as ever he had caſt a Devil out of one Maid, preſently they muſt be caſt inro Priſon; without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had not <hi>God</hi> come in with freſh ſupplies of comfort, theſe poor men would have been at a great loſs, they would have been much diſheartned in their work? and this the Devid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47061:4"/>knew would be a very great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to them;<note place="margin">Ezek. <hi>1.16.</hi>
               </note> but now my Friends, behold a wheel within a wheel, all this while the providence of <hi>God</hi> doth ſeem to go upon the wheels, as if he had not cared what became of his Servants, nor what became of his own glory, and of theſe poor ſouls that he had commanded theſe men to come into <hi>Macedonia</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert; but now my Friends here is a wheel within a wneel, here is the over-ruling, and the infinite wiſdom of <hi>God,</hi> appearing in the very nick of time, catching the crafty in his own device,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 5.12.13.</note> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the counſel of the wicked and a crafty Devil, that having vented his malice, and his rage againſt the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>mod,</hi> thought himſelf now ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of the day; and that his Kingdom ſhould not be moleſted in that place; but we ſee, that though the Devil is called an old Serpent, yet the Antient of days did out-wit him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.22. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> and though the Devil is called a Lyon for his ſtrength and power, and a a roaring Lyon for his fury; yet the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> was too many for him, our Lord Chriſt did make this very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ageſ of Sathan, this diſcovery of his malice, a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47061:4"/>means to throw down the Devils Kingdom, and to exalt and propagate h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s own; for we ſee, that when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> was brought into the Priſon, inſtead of being diſcouraged, they ſung Pſalms; inſtead of lying there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Irons had entred into their ſouls, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Priſoners bands was unlooſned; well, what follows: the Goaler he comes in, and he finds the doors open, he thought his priſoners had been fled; and, now what courſe doth he take? he draws out his ſword to murder himſelf, he had been doing what lay in him to murther his ſoul all the days of his life before, and now he was about, by one act, to murther both ſoul and body together.</p>
            <p>Now without queſtion, the Devil that had encoutaged him in the exaſperating of his cruelty on theſe worthy ſervants of <hi>God,</hi> he was now as ready to rejoyce in the downfall of this poor Creature.</p>
            <p>My Friends, by the way I pray excuſe this digreſſion; O let it be a means to make us have very low contemptible thoughts of this ill conditioned Maſter the Devil, that when his ſervants have done him the utmoſt ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vice they can, he is ſo far from having ever the better thoughts of them, and from loving of them the better, that he doth wait his oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and doth prompt them on in thoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47061:5"/>actions, that he may bring inevitable ruine and and deſtruction upon them. I do verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, that when the Devil ſaw the poor mans ſword drawn, and the point of it ready to be ſet again his breaſt, that he did rejoyce to ſee the poor man ready to tumble head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into everlaſting flames; but now this wiſe <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.14.</note> whoſe head is as white as wool, did fruſtrate the expectation of this ſubtile ſerpent, he did catch the crafty in his own devices; you need not queſtion but the Devil did endeavour to help forward this cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which this Goaler did exerciſe towards theſe ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vants of <hi>God;</hi> and you may ſee this cruelty of his, <hi>God</hi> did ſo by his wiſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence order it, that it did tend to his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>O happy was it for the poor moaler, that <hi>God</hi> did finiſh two works in one journey; that he came to deliver the bodies of his ſervants from a temporal priſon, and did deliver the ſoul of the Goaler from the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon of Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire. Well now, in the verſe before my Text, you ſee the Goaler coming trembling before the Priſoners of hope, he that before thought <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> not worthy to live on the earth, did now come, and fall down to the earth at their Feet, and ſaid, <hi>what ſhall I do to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47061:5"/>be ſaved?</hi> O what a ſerious queſtion was here? well now, the words in my Text, are an anſwer to this ſerious queſtion; why ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> And thus being come to the words of my Text, I ſhall briefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them into two parts: Firſt, here is an exhortation to a very ſerious and weighty du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that is, <hi>believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 2dly.</hi> Here is a prevailing excitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtir him up to the performance of this duty in theſe words, <hi>and thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> in the exhortation we have ſeveral particulars, in this firſt general: Firſt, here is the act, and that is <hi>believe. 2dly.</hi> Here is the object, <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 3dly.</hi> Take notice of the perſons here, that is preſſing this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation on him, and that was <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas:</hi> Thoſe that had been ſcourged and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned by him, they were now preaching the Goſpel to him, and without queſtion, with bowels of compaſſion to his pretious ſouls. They did not now think of Revenge, and did not now, while this poor man was in a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Agony, take there advantage againſt him, and ſay, thou haſt been cruel to us, and now ſhift for thy ſelf as well as thou canſt; no, for firſt they hinder him from ſelf-Murther, and <hi>2dly.</hi> they preach the Goſpel to him, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47061:6"/>on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> in the fourth and laſt place, the perſon exhorted to this Duty, and that was the moaler, one that had been a violent perſecutor, and he is here exhorted to believe in Chriſt. From whence my Friends, take notice of this; that 'tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the greateſt ſinner to get a broaken heart; one would have thought, that if any man ſhould have gone without a broken heart, and without Chriſt, and mercy, a perſecuting Goaler ſhould, that had perſecuted thoſe bleffed ſervants of <hi>God,</hi> that did come on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe among them, to do their ſouls good.</p>
            <p>By the way my Friends, take encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you that are the greateſt ſinners here, (though not to continue in your ſins) yet to wait on <hi>God</hi> in Goſpel Ordinances, for you know not how ſoon God may be pleaſed to work on your Souls, and to turn you from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto <hi>God;</hi> I ſhall ſtand no longer, before I come to the main Obſervation that I would preſent you with, which is this that every true believer ſhall be ſaved, <hi>believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> my Friends, I having elſewhere made an attempt on theſe words, and made entrance into them, I ſhall not now ſtand to ſpend much time in the Doctrinal part, but only confirm it by a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47061:6"/>few Scriptures, that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes every word may be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the firſt in <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. He <hi>that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaved;</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have in the 3d. Chap. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> 16. <hi>v. For God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life;</hi> and in the 36. <hi>v.</hi> of the ſame Chapter, <hi>he that believeth on the Son, hath everlaſting Life;</hi> he hath it already in its incoation, and when he dyes, he ſhall have it in its conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Now my Friends, I ſhall come to the Application, which is that I mainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, in ſetting upon this, ſubject this day; and in the firſt place, if every true believer, ſhall be ſaved, this is uſeful; firſt, by way of information. 2dly. By way of examination. Thirdly, By way of conſolation. Fourthly, By way of exhortation. Fifthly, By way of Inſtruction. Firſt, 'tis uſeful by way of Information, if every true Believer ſhall be ſaved, then it may inform us of the infinite and boundleſs love of God to all true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. O! well may the Apoſtle ſay in the 3d. of <hi>Iohn, v.</hi> 16. <hi>God ſo ſaved the World.</hi> O my Friends, their is ſo much contained in this word <hi>ſo,</hi> as cannot be uttered by the Creature, for when Wiſdom it ſelf was ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47061:7"/>of it, he puts it off with a <hi>ſo,</hi> not as thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt could not have manifeſted the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> depth of the love of God, but becauſe, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he could have done it, we being but finite Creatures, were not in a capacity to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that boundleſs depth of this love of God to poor ſinners: My Friends, I may alude to thoſe words of <hi>Job.</hi> 11.7, 8, 9. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching, find out God? canſt thou find ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Almighty unto perfection? it is as high as Heaven; what can'ſt thou know? the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure whereof is longer then the Earth, broader then the Sea.</hi> We ſee ſuch is the immenſity and greatneſs of this love of God to poor ſinners, that 'tis unſpeakable and glorious, and I may ſay of it, that 'tis that, we cannot find out to perfection; <hi>'tis as high as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; what can we do? the meaſure thereof is longer then the Earth, and broader then the Sea.</hi> This love of God to poor ſinners, it may appear in the higheſt Heaven, for not a Soul that is in glory, but is beholding to this boundleſs love of God for their ſalvation. <hi>God ſo loved the World,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt puts it off as it were with a queſtion, as if it were that which cannot be uttered, nor indeed can it be uttered by the Creature; for if all the Angels in Heaven ſhould undertake to ſet forth the love of God, in ſending of Chriſt to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47061:7"/>dye for poor ſinners, they muſt have ſo much time as will run parallel with the Line of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, or elſe they will, never accompliſh their work; for, ſo long will this love of God extend it ſelf in the higheſt degree the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is capable of.</p>
            <p>Oh my friends, was it not wonderful love in God, that he ſhould ſend his Son to dye for Rebels; that he that had but one natural Son, ſhould give him up to the death for us that were proclaiming open War againſt him by our ſins: Oh wonderful boundleſs love, well may the Apoſtle ſay indeed, in the 5th. of <hi>Romans,</hi> the 8th. <hi>v. Herein God commended his love towards us; in that while we were ſinners, Chriſt dyed for us,</hi> that is the firſt. 2ly It may inform us of the glorious effects of the death and ſufferings of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for though the love of God was the impulſive cauſe of our ſalvation, yet it was the death and ſuffering, the active and paſſive obedience of Jeſus Chriſt, that was the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cauſe thereof; and therefore ſaith the Lord in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 53. when the Holy Ghoſt had been there ſpending a whole Chapter in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the ſufferings of Chriſt for poor ſinners, at length he comes to ſhew the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and the ſweet, and glorious effects produced thereby, in <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Therefore will I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47061:8"/>devide him a Portion with the great, and he ſhall divide the ſpoyl with the ſtrong becauſe he hath poured out his ſoul unto death. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I divide him a Portion with the great;</hi> what <hi>great</hi> is this? Why 'tis the great Devil, that is ſo great in power, that he leads Captive the greateſt part of the World; and <hi>he ſhall devide the ſpoyl with the ſtrong,</hi> which is the ſame mentioned before, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Holy Ghoſt in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to enjeminate expreſſions, as if the Lord ſhould have ſaid, becauſe a poor man hath ſinned, therefore the Devil thinks for to have the Souls of all the Men and Women in the World; but ſaith God, <hi>I will divide him a Portion with the great, and he ſhall divide the ſpoil with the ſtrong;</hi> as if the Lord ſhould have ſaid, my Son ſhall have ſome Souls, the Devil ſhould not have all; for there is ſome that I am reſolved ſhall be the fruit of my Sons Travel, as in the 11. <hi>v.</hi> of the 53 of <hi>Iſa. He ſhall ſee of the Travel of his Soul, and ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi> and Alegorical Metaphor, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from a Woman in Travel, that though ſhe hath a ſharp Travel, yet rejoyceth when a man is born into the world; ſo though Chriſt did indure ſore pangs in working out the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Elect, yet <hi>he ſhall ſee of the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel of his Soul; I will divide him a Portion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47061:8"/>with the great:</hi> Gods people are called his Portion, as in <hi>Deut</hi> 32. <hi>v</hi> 9. <hi>The Lords Portion is his People.</hi> Well ſaith God, <hi>my Son ſhall have his Portion in Men, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which the Devil doth think to bring to everlaſting ruine and deſtruction;</hi> well this is the ſecond thing: O my Friends, that time and it ength would permit, for the more clearing up of it is great truth, to ſhew the glorious effects of the death and ſuffering of the Lord Jeſus chriſt, towards believers, for the effects of his death, doth extend it ſelf to their adoption, and comfort, and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and happineſs, and glory hereafter; all theſe benefits, &amp; many more are the glorious effects of the death and ſuffering of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Then in the third place, if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true believer ſhall be received into glory, it may inform us how much we are ingaged to love the good ſpirit of <hi>God,</hi> that doth ſeal up to our Souls, our intereſt in Chriſt; in whom alone 'tis, that we are brought to glory; 'tis the work of Gods ſpirit, to ſhow us our want of Chriſt; and when he hath thus convinced us of our ſins, then 'tis the work of this bleſſed ſpirit of <hi>God</hi> to bare up our Souls under the dreadful apprehenſions of <hi>Gods</hi> wrath, that is due to us for ſin; ſo 'tis the work of the bleſſed Spirit of God to help the Soul to ſee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47061:9"/>that Chriſt dyed for Sinners, and that he hath dyed for thee; O Soul, thou art a Believer, 'tis the holy ſpirit of God that doth comfort the Soul in trouble; that doth ſettle the Soul in fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that doth preſerve the Soul in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering ſlate, when it would be turned to the right hand, or to the left; O my Friends, one may ſay of the Spirit of God, as <hi>David</hi> did of the City of God, <hi>glorious things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thee,</hi> ſo I may ſay, glorious things are ſpoken of thee, O bleſſed Spirit of God; and therefore as in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 30. <hi>Grieve not the holy Spirit of God, whereby you are ſealed up to the day of Redemption.</hi> In the fourth place, if it be ſo, that every true Believer ſhall be ſaved, then it may inform us of the falthood of thoſe erronious Tennets, which hold forth of a poſſibility of falling away from true faith; <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> did net ſay to the Goaler, if thou believeſt, and continueſt to believe, thou ſhalt be ſaved, <hi>but if thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt, thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi> once a believer and ever a believer. My friends, I hope you have not forgot how I did endeavour in twelve particulars to ſhew you from whence the believers perſeverence doth ariſe, and all the <hi>Armenian</hi> Tennets in the world ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to ſtrike at the Root of any of theſe twelve foundations of a Believers perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47061:9"/>As firſt, thou that art a Believer, thou haſt the eternal decree of God ingaged for thy perſeverance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 <hi>chap.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>v. Heb.</hi> 6.17. Thou haſt likewiſe the Eternal love of God, as another ground of thy perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>I have loved thee with an everlaſting love, therefore with love and kindneſs have I drawn thee;</hi> my Friends, I wonder how men that pretend to have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhould be blinded ſo by the God of this world, to think that the ſame everlaſting love, that did ingage God to ſet his love on us, ſhould ever be turned into hatred, ſo as to leave us to our wills, and ſo to periſh for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; likewiſe the wiſdom of God is engaged herein; Chriſt makes it a mark of fooliſh man, that doth begin te build a houſe, &amp; is not able to finiſh it; thou that art a believing Soul, thou art Gods ſpiritual building; and if he ſhould begin to build, and ſhould not finiſh it, it would demonſtrate great folly in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, which to affert would be no leſs then blaſphemy, God being the fountain of wiſdom; likewiſe the faithfulneſs of God is engaged in it. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.24, 25. <hi>Faithful is he that hath called you who alſo will do it,</hi> will do what? you may read in the 23 <hi>v. And the very God of peace ſanctifie you wholly; and I pray God your whole ſpirit, and ſoul, and body
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47061:10"/>be preſerv'd blameleſs unto the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Till Chriſt ſhall come, by judgment, or by death, that Soul in whom this good work is begun, ſhall be carried on, <hi>Phil</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>He that hath begun a good work, will finiſh it,</hi> and we ſhewed likewiſe 'tis clear from the new Covenant of grace, that he hath entred into a new Covenant with the people, and he hath therein engaged himſelf, that he will put his fear into our hearts, that we ſhall not depart from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. Likewiſe the power of God is ingaged herein to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver every true believer from total falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from God, 2 <hi>Fet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Who are kept by the power of God, through Faith unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Likewiſe alſo the glory of the Son of God is engaged in it; Chriſt is the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſpiritual building, he is the chief Corner Stone. Now my Friends, I pray mind it, whenſoever a houſe falls, the foundation is uſually defective, and the Corner ſtone will be ſure to fall: nay, he is the top-ſtone too, as you may ſee in <hi>Zachary.</hi> Now Chriſt being all theſe in the ſpiritual ſuperſtructure, it muſt be, that Jeſus Chriſt muſt fall himſelf, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a true believer doth finally, ſall off from God. Again, we ſhewed likewiſe it doth ariſe from the influence, that the bleſſed Spirit of God hath on the hearts of thoſe that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47061:10"/>are believers, as in the 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>But you have an Unction from the Holy One, and you know all things;</hi> he had been ſhewing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what a ſight of Antichriſts and Apoſtates there were; but ſaith he, <hi>you have received an Unction from the Holy One;</hi> you have that which they want, they had only an outſide profeſſion, but they wanted the inward teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the ſpirit, as in the 26 and 27th. <hi>ver. Iſa.</hi> 59.19. You may there ſee how God doth keep a ſoul in a perſevering frame, <hi>So ſhall they fear the Name of the Lord from the Weſt, &amp; his glory from the Riſing of the Sun, when the enemy ſhall come in like a Flood, the ſpirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a Standard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</hi> The words are very emphatical, whether they do point at the Devil, or at the corruptions of our own hearts, which are the greateſt perſecutors of the godly; 'tis a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary expreſſion, taken from Souldiers, when they lift up their Enſigns in defiance of their Enemies; and as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>upon this Rock have I built my Church, that the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it,</hi> ſo ſaith the Spirit, <hi>here when the Enemy breaks in like a Flood,</hi> then ſhall the Spirit of the Lord <hi>lift up his Standard againſt them;</hi> Iſa. 30. <hi>v.</hi> 21. You may ſee how the ſpirit doth proceed in hi work, to keep the Soul in a perſevering frame,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47061:11"/>whenſoever the poor Soul is ready to turn to the Right hand, or to the Left, then he doth whiſper a ſweet word in their ear, <hi>this is the way, walk in it,</hi> and truly that is a notable word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>And I will direct their work in truth,</hi> 'tis God by the influence of his ſpirit, directing of our works in truth, that doth keep us from falling away from God. I hope my Friends, theſe are enough to confirm this fourth truth, that true believers cannot fall off from God. Fifthly, It may inform us of the vaſt difference that is between the ſtate of true Believers, and the ſtate of Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; for if you look in thoſe Scriptures wk mentioned, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that believeth not. ſhall be damned,</hi> and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>John</hi> 3. there you may ſee the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſet down, <hi>He that believeth on the Son hath everlaſting life; and he that believeth not on the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but the Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true believer is ſaid to have everlaſting life, that is, he hath the aſſurance of it ſooner or later; he hath it in this life, in its incoati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though not in its conſummation. I pray my Friends, if you remember no more, carry away this, that if Heaven, and Eternal life is not within you, while you are in this world,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47061:11"/>you ſhall never enter into Heavenly or Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, when you ſhall leave this world; Now herein appears the vaſt difference that is between the ſtate of a Believer and an Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; as a believer hath the Heaven of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Light from God, and the ſame ſpiritual love to God, &amp; the ſame ſpiritual joy in God, and the ſame ſpiritual Communion with God, now in this life, as they ſhall have in the life to come, in reſpect of the nature and quality thereof, though not in reſpect of the quantity; ſo likewiſe a wicked man hath the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l darkneſs in his underſtanding, and the ſame irregularality in his affection, and the ſame contumacy in his will now, as he will have in Hell, in reſpect of the nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity thereof, though not in reſpect of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and quantity; now helliſh Drunkards make themſelves Drunk with Wine and ſtrong bear, and in Hell God will make them pledg the Devil at a full Cup of his wrath; which being powered into the Cup of his Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will make them Drunk for ever and ever; the Helliſh Adulterer burns in his Luſt here, and <hi>God</hi> will make him burn in Hell for it hereafter: As heavenly Saints love <hi>God,</hi> and propound his glory as their ultimate end in all their duties; ſo heilliſh Sinners hate <hi>God,</hi> and propound their own glory as their ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47061:12"/>end in duties; as believers are daily more and more compleat in vertue, ſo unbelievers are daily more and more repleat with Vice; and thus we ſee the vaſt difference that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween believers and unbelievers in this life; and look upon them at the hour of death, and ſee what a vaſt difference there will be then between them, as in <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32. <hi>The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is driven away in his wickedneſs, but the Righteous hath hope on his death;</hi> and look upon them at the Reſurrection, and ſee what a vaſt difference there is between them, as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>And many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the Earth, ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting contempt;</hi> and look upon them at the denunciation of that dreadful ſentence, and ſee the vaſt difference that is between them, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.33, 34. where the Righteous &amp; the believer is ſet <hi>on his right hand,</hi> and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer <hi>on the left, Then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand, come ye bleſſed of my Father;</hi> come poor ſoul, thou haſt called me to come to thee many a time, in cuty then come thou now to me; the world looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee to be a curſed Creature, but I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce thee bleſſed; it may be, whilſt thou wert in the world, the Foxes had a priviledg above thee, they had holes to hide their heads
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47061:12"/>in; But now there is a Kingdom prepared for thee, but now ſee what will become of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, as in the 41. <hi>v.</hi> here is a dreadful ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſt againſt them. <hi>Depart from me,</hi> here is a ſeparation from all joy and happineſs; you ſaid to me in your life-time, <hi>depart from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for we deſire not the knowledg of the wars, now depart from me ye Curſed, into everlaſting fire,</hi> there is the extremity of pain and torment, thou waſt one that did burn in thy luſts here, and thou waſt one that was inflamed with thy luſts, or with wine and ſtrong drink, or with hatred againſt me; now go into everlaſting fire, it was the Devil whoſe voice thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt obey, and whoſe work thou wouldeſt do, and now thou ſhalt have enough of him: now here you may ſee the vaſt difference between the ſtate of all true believers and unbelievers.</p>
            <p>Now believers, <hi>thy ſhall ceaſe from all their mourning, and all their ſorrow ſhell be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed into joy,</hi> then thou ſhalt have joy without ſorrow, and health without ſickneſs, and life without death, and ſhall have the ſhinings of Gods Countenance, without the leaſt mixture of the hiding of his face, and as for thou that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t an unbeliever, what wilt thou do, 2 vaſt d fference there will be between thy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and a true believers, when thou art caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting flames, which I wiſh that none
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47061:13"/>here may experience the torments of, when thou ſhalt never more have the leaſt hope of the leaſt Ray of the Son of Conſolation ſhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on thee: Oh then what woe and terror will ſurprize thy Soul, and what unſpeakable horror, to think that thou haſt been all thy life time heaping up to thy ſelf wrath againſt the day of wrath.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have proceeded to other inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but I ſhall defer them till the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon: Conſider what hath been ſaid, and the Lord give you underſtanding.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the Morning Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47061:13"/>
            <p>THen in the ſixth place, if it be ſo, that all true believers ſhall be ſaved, it may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us of the great neceſſity we have of hearing the Word Preached, though my Friends, God is able to convert without means; he is a free agent, he can work how he will, and when he will, but Preaching is the ordinary means whereby <hi>God</hi> doth turn Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from Satan to <hi>God,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4 4, 5. where you may ſee there is a molton Sea, which was a Type of Chriſt, <hi>it ſtood upon</hi> 12. <hi>Oxen, three looking towards the North, and three looking towrds the Weſt, and three looking towards the South, and three looking towards the Eaſt;</hi> and if you look into the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> there you ſhall ſee the Elect ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and from the North, and from the South, and there is twelve doors open in the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> three North, three Weſt, three South, and three Eaſt, Chriſt he is the Molten Sea, through
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47061:14"/>whom 'tis we are brought to Life, he it is that is the Sea of Grace and mercy for poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: therefore, if you would have this Sea of Grace, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we muſt have an eye unto the twelve Oxen, the twelve A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and their ſucceſſors, which are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, and faith the Apoſtle in <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.17. <hi>So faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God.</hi> My Friends, I durſt not limit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo as to ſay, there is no way to convert a Soul, but by Preaching of the Goſpel; but this is the ordinary way God is pleaſed to make uſe of, for the opening of their eyes, that are blinded by the god of this world; for we are all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally blind, and we muſt lye by the way ſide, to be cured of this blindneſs; the Preaching of the word, they are Gods Pools of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> whereby he doth cure thoſe that are troubled with ſpiritual lameneſs, and thoſe that come into Congregations poſſeſſed with Devils, as in <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.23.24.25. He caſts out a Devil of Pride out of one Soul, and a Devil of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetuouſneſs out of another Soul, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of Luſt out of another, and thoſe devilliſh Luſts Chriſt doth caſt out while we ere in the Synagogue.</p>
            <p>Then 7thly. It may inform us what ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies they are to our immortal Souls, that go
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47061:14"/>about to deprive us of the means of Grace; you ſee Preaching is the ordinary means for the Converſion of Souls, ſo they muſt be ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murderers that go about to hinder the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Eighthly. It may inform us of the unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs and ſenſoriouſneſs of thoſe perſons that for ſmal differences from them, in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Religion, will ſend whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to everlaſting perdition, that if they cannot comply with them in every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, they are preſently all damned: But we ſee that it is not being of this or that perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that will bring us to Heaven, but belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Jeſus Chriſt; but yet my Friends, though ſuch a thing is deſirable, and we hope will be when the Lyon ſhall lye down with the Lamb, and the Leopard ſhall eat graſs with the Oxe, yet in the mean while, let us not paſs ſuch uncharitable cenſures on thoſe that cannot comply with us in every circumſtantial point in Religion; you ſee faith is the main thing that the Apoſtle drives at; believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that is the main thing that is to be looked at; I ſhall now come to an uſe of examination, if it be ſo that none but true believers ſhall be ſaved, then it lyes upon us to ſee whether we are ſuch believers or not: My Friends, if any of us were but to lay out a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47061:15"/>little money upon a purchaſe, though of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle value, how circumſpect ſhould we be, leaſt our evidences ſhould prove falſe, and this care is not diſcommendable neither; but how will this condemn the practice of the greateſt part of the World, that are ſo ſtrict and careful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout trifles, and neglect the concerns of their immortal Souls; I ſhall endeavour to lay down ſome Rules and Tryals, which by the aſſiſtance of Gods ſpirit, we may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are true believers, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as are in a ſtate of Salvation. Firſt, would'ſt thou know whether thou art a true believer, then try whether thou doſt know God, for we will never venture any great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment upon a perſon that we know little of; thou that art a believer, thou haſt greater concerns to venture on God, then ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds; me-thinks I hear ſome ſay, what do you think we don't know God to be our Father, and Chriſt our Redeemer. My Friends have you any reality of the knowledg of God in your Souls: have you a practical knowledg of him, ſee what our Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3. <hi>And this is Life Etarnal, that they may know the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent;</hi> the Practical knowledg of God is Eternal life, in its incoation. My Friends, do you know God ſo in his power, as to fear him;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47061:15"/>and in his mercy to love him, and in his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciency, not to commit any ſin in ſecret, though the eye of the Creator be upon thee, this was a ſign that <hi>Joſeph</hi> had a true knowledg of God, that when he was tempted to ſin, which poſſibly might have been hid from the eyes of the World, yet he dared not to commit it, but on the contrary, if you know ſo little of God in his mercy, that it doth not draw out your love to him; and know him ſo little in his Juſtice, that you ſee no need of Jeſus Chriſt to be your Redeemer, and you know him not in his faithfulneſſes, that you dare not truſt him, then 'tis a ſign thou art an unbeliever: canſt thou ſay with <hi>Paul, I know whom I have believed,</hi> 2 Tim. 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. If thou art one, that art a true believer then thou art one that haſt an indeared affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ro God; when a Soul believes that God hath ſent his dear Son to dye for him, and this comes to be realized to the Soul, that ſoul is ſet all in a flame with love to God. Friends, obſerve this, that proportionable to the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions we have of the love of God to us, in Jeſus Chriſt, ſuch is the manifeſtation of our love to God; what is the reaſon the Martyrs have embraced the flames with ſuch courage, which at other times it may be, a few days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they were ready to ſink at the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47061:16"/>of the bitter cup they were to drink, but the clear ſence they had of the love of God to their ſouls. We know this my Friends, that the greater and clearer evidences we have of that good, which at preſent we do receive from a Friend, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hopes to receive from them for the future, it doth abundantly ſtir up our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and inflame our love towards them, if we look into the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> we may ſee that God hath put Faith and Love together; and what God hath joyned together, let no man put aſunder, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. <hi>And now abideth Faith, Hope, and Charity, Gal</hi> 5, 6. <hi>Neither Circumciſion availeth any thing nor Uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, but faith which worketh by love.</hi> Friends, how do you find it, what love have you to, the worſhip of God, &amp; to the Ordinances of God, and to the people of God; do your ſouls bear you witneſs, that you can ſay of the word of God, as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>that 'tis ſweeter than the honey, or the honey-comb;</hi> in the 3d. place, Try it by your hope likewiſe; a true faith doth always accompany a true hope: 'Tis true Friends, we had need be criticol about theſe things, for go and ask an unbeliever whether he loves God, and he will anſwer you, 'tis pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he ſhould live elſe; and again ask them, whether they hope to have Salvation by Chriſt alone; yes ſay they, who do you think we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47061:16"/>ſhould have it from beſides, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. But what ſaith the Apoſtle of this hope, <hi>and every man that hath this hope, he purifies himſelf as he is pure.</hi> My Friends, all the difference, that is between faith and hope is this. Faith doth reſpect the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the promiſe, and hope doth reſpect the goodneſs of the thing promiſed, and where one of theſe are, there they are both, for they both go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but now you may ſay what is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this purifying himſelf; as he is pure, can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y one be ſo pure as God is: My Friends, 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impoſſible, that the Creature ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to that degree of perfection and purity that is in God, pure ſignifies to be without mixture; a perſon may be ſaid to be purely evil, as God is purely good; he purifies himſelf as he is pure, that is, he hath not a heart for God, &amp; another for the world; he is really ſuch as he ſeems to be, he is without hypocriſie. 4thly. Again, would'ſt thou know the ſoundneſs of thy Faith, then try i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by thy conſtant implacable hatred of ſin; this we may ſee laid down as a true mark of Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>Purifying their hearts by Faith:</hi> Faith doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſoul with a Crucified Jeſus, as Crucified for it in particular; the formal Profeſſor pleaſeth himſelf with this, that Chriſt dyed for ſinners, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e are all ſinners. My Friends, there is nothing that gives ſuch a mortal wound to ſin, in the ſoul of believers, as when they do apprehend that Chriſt did ſuffer ſuch grievous things, for its
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47061:17"/>ſelf in particular. 5thly. Wouldeſt thou know, whether thy faith be right, then ſee if thou haſt a high eſteem of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Unto you therefore that believe, he is precious,</hi> or he is a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; a true believer, he looks upon it as his honour, that he is a member of Chriſts miſtical body, that he is a branch in that bleſſed Vine; he looks upon it as his honour, that Chriſt will look upon him as his Servant; as the Emperor <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> ſaid, <hi>he looked upon it to be more honour to him, that he was a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, then that he was Emperour of the World.</hi> But I have ſeen ſuch Chriſtians that would be very forward to own the people of God, and Meſſengers of Chriſt, in times of proſperity; but when the ways of God hath been perſecuted, &amp; the Ordinances of Chriſt hath been trampled under feet, then they would look upon them, as if they had never ſeen them before: My Friends, this is a bad ſign of a true Faith, and of a good Chriſtian, to you that believe he is an honour; my Friends, is Chriſt precious to you in all his Offices, as King, Prieſt, and Prophet; thou that art a believer, I can tell how 'tis with thee, as well as thy ſelf; thou doſt never more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, then when thou canſt experience the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Chriſt in thy Soul, in ſubduing of thy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and bringing under the Old man; and is he pretious to thee in all his attributes? a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, God is precious to him in his mercies, but as for the power of God, and the Juſtice of God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47061:17"/>they cannot indure to hear of; let a Miniſter go and tell them of the terrors of God, they will preſently cry, Oh there is a Legal Preacher in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, enough to make one run mad; &amp; in a word, to a true believer, Chriſt is precious to him in all his Offices and attributes, and in all his providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial diſpenſations, and in all his promiſes, and in his threatnings, he is precious to every true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Again, ſixthly, wouldeſt thou know whether thou art indeed a true believer, then ſee whether thou haſt the witneſs of it in thy ſelf, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.6. <hi>He that believeth, hath the Witneſs in himſelf;</hi> Oh but me-thinks I hear ſome poor ſoul ready to ſay; Oh, if it muſt be ſo, I am in a worſe condition then I was aware of; I thought I could experienced ſome of the other Tryals, but I have ſo little of the ſpirits witneſs in me, that I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether I have any true faith: Now the Devil is very ſubtile, as he will perſwade a wicked man, that he hath the marks of a true believer, ſo he will perſwade a true believer, that he hath them not, when he hath them; as for example, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a perſon is in great trouble, for fear they don't love God, they come into the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and there it may be, God hath directed his Miniſter to ſuch a ſubject, where he hath been treating on ſuch a truth of Gods love to us, and of our love to him; if God hath loved thee, then he hath ſubdued thy Corruptions, theſe little
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47061:18"/>Foxes he hath taken and deſtroyed; now it may be the ſpirit of God hath ſet home this word on the ſoul, and that he can ſay, this hath been my condition. Now Friends, there was the witneſs that we are ſpeaking of <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. <hi>The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit bearing witneſs with our ſpirit, that we are the Children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God.</hi> Now my Friends, you that are ſo ready to ſay, that you have not the witneſs of God in you; wouldeſt thou part with that little glimme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing hope thou haſt of true Faith, for the greateſt Eſtate that a Wicked man hath in the world? to ſaith the ſoul, I would not; and that is a ſign that thou haſt the witneſs in thee, though the ſpirit of God hath not cleared it up ſo to thee, as thou deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt but be thankful to God for it, and take heed thou doſt not provoke the Lord to take away that little comfort thou haſt.</p>
            <p>Eighthly. If thou art one that hath true faith, thou mayeſt know it by this, it doth ſo realize the glory that is to be revea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to thy ſoul, that it makes thee earneſt in the proſecution of the means that God hath appointed in order to the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of glory; this we ſhall make to appear by comparing two Scriptures together, in the 11th. of <hi>Hebrews,</hi> you may ſee that Faith is the evidence of things not ſeen, and the ſubſtance of things hoped for, now if you do but look all along in this Chapter, he comes to ſhow what lorious effects Faith doth produce in thoſe that it doth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47061:18"/>realize the glory that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to come unto them; he telleth us 'tis the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen, that is not ſeen with an eye of eaſon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.23, 24. <hi>then ſaid one to him, Lord, are there few that he ſaved?</hi> now ſee, Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt doth not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him according to his Queſtion, but doth propoſe to him an exhortation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſtir him up to a weighty duty, <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrate gate;</hi> as if Chriſt had ſaid, what needeſt thou to trouble thy ſelf whether many or few ſhall be ſaved? if thou art one that ſtrives like a man in an Agony (for ſo it may be rendered) to thruſt in at the ſtraight gate, that will be an evidence unto thee, that thou art one that ſhall be ſaved. Friends, how doth the hope of glory ſpur you on to duty: doth thy Faith realize the things of another world to you, that it makes you run in the paths of Gods commandments. But if on the contrary, if thou doſt pretend to have Faith, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, go on in a formal lazy profeſſion of Religion; 'tis a ſign thou never had the things of another world realized to thee; ſuch as are our evidences for the attainment of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture good, ſuch will be our endeavours, in the means whereby we are to attain it, if thou haſt a well-grounded hope for ſalvation in the world to come, it will make thee earneſt in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47061:19"/>thy endeavours for the attainment of it. In the next place, another ſign of true Faith is this, if thou art a true believer, then thy faith doth enable thee to overcome the world; this we may ſee in the 12 <hi>Rev. and there appeared a great wonder in Heaven, a Woman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loathed with the Sun and the Moon under her feet.</hi> By the Women we underſtand the whole Church of God, and every perticular member thereof, and by the Moon we underſtand the World.</p>
            <p>And as the Moon is very unſtable in her mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and always increaſing and decreaſing, ſo there is no certainty at all in Creature injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And the Sun is never eclipſed, but when the Moon comes between us, and the Sun; and ſo my Friends, the Moon, this wo ld, is that which doth make an interpoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and his people; how doth the joys of this world eat out the comforts which we ſhould have enjoyed. My Friends, 'tis a hard thing to keep the world under our feet, for 'tis a round thing, and I will tell you how true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers do come to get the world under their Feet.</p>
            <p>You that have once injoyed the glorious beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhining in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſouls, the pittiful things of this Wo ld would ſeem as nothing: Now my Friends ſee how it is with you, which is greater in your
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47061:19"/>eye, the Sun or the Moon; which if it were put to your choyce, would you take to live in the midſt of proſperity without God, or in the midſt of adverſity with God.</p>
            <p>Again, in the next place, try thy Faith by thy Repentance; I know there is much diſpute concerning this, ſome hold that Faith is wrought before Repentance, and ſome on the contrary; but truly my Friends, I am of neither of their judgments, for my judgment is, that all graces are wrought in the ſoul at one and the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime; &amp; though Repentance is made manifeſt in the ſoul before Faith, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. <hi>Repent you, and believe the Goſpel;</hi> Friends, what Repentance have you got, I thank God ſay you, I have Repented long agoe, though I cannot talk as ſome can, and make ſo many words, I cannot commit any ſin, but my heart ſmites me for it: Oh my Friends, there is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of Repentance that a ſinner may have, and yet may go without a true Repentance; there is an over-lay and ſlight repentance, and ſuch a repentance had <hi>Ahab,</hi> and then there is diſpairing repentance, and ſuch a repentance bad <hi>Judas:</hi> but for this Evangelical repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, 'tis ſuch a grace that few attain to it, not ſcarce one among twenty, and without this, Evangelical repentance, there is no true grace in the ſoul; and I ſhall endeavour to ſhow, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47061:20"/>Faith and Repentance is wrought together for repentance without faith, will end in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparation; and faith without repentance will end in preſumption.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, if thou art one that hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed true faith, thou art made willing to ſuffer whatſoever God ſhould be pleaſed to inflict on thee, this ſaith the Apoſtle, where he ſpeaks there concerning perſecution <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.29. <hi>For unto you 'tis given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake;</hi> this true Faith, it makes the ſoul will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to ſuffer for God, whatſoever the wicked adverſaries of the people of God ſhall be pleaſed to lay on them; O ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the ſoul, ſhall I be unwilling to indure a little ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for his ſake, that was expoſed to ſuch ſuffering for me: O ſaith the ſoul, ſhall not I be willing to ſuffer a little affliction from God, whether poverty, wants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſickneſs, or the like, ſeeing the Lord Jeſus Chriſt was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented for my ſake to a be man of ſorrow, and acquainted with grief, for to ſuffer both hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thurſt, and ſhall not we be willing to ſuffer for God, whatſoever he is pleaſed to call us to, ſeeing he hath pleaſed to do ſo much for us, as he hath done.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for this Uſe of Examination; I ſhould have proceeded to a Uſe of Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47061:20"/>on to true believers, for this Doctrine affoards a ſpring of comfort unto ſuch which I ſhould only hint at, firſt by way of privation, ſhowing from what they are delivered: econdly by way of proviſion, what unexpreſſable &amp; unconceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able glory, God hath laid up in ſtore for them, which I would have willingly inlarged upon: There was likewiſe on my ſpirit, a Uſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in which I would have moved thoſe who have been participaters of this pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous Faith. 1. To be thankful for it, to him, from whom they have received it, as the gift of God. 2. To let nothing be wanting for the nouriſhing, and for the ſtrengthening of it, by the Application of former experiences of Gods goodneſs, &amp; alſo to be careful that they wound not, not weaken their Faith by running them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into thoſe ſtreights and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncies which they have not a clear and ſpecial call unto, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon a civil, or religious account; but I muſt paſs by thoſe things, becauſe my time is already paſſed by, and conclude with one Uſe of Exhortation, or rather of invitation to thoſe which are yet out of Chriſt; and oh that God would be pleaſed to put ſome word into my mouth, which might beget in thee an earneſt deſire, and panting after an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, the glorious object of our faith! oh that I could hear ſome of you crying our with the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47061:21"/>poor Goaler, <hi>what ſhall I do to be ſav'd;</hi> in the time of ſickneſs, who will not cry out, what ſhall I do to be reſtored to my health, the want of outward mercies are quickly felt, but how few are ſenſible of their want in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals; beware likewiſe that the Devil enſnare you into deſparation, by perſwading t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee that thou haſt no faith, and therefore art a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, for there is not a Saint on earth, nor an Angel in Heaven, to whom Gods final repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation is revealed, touching any particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon yet in this life, who hath not ſinned the ſin againſt he Holy Ghoſt; be not therefore by theſe wiles of Sathan diſcouraged from waiting on the Ordinances, or make thee ſay I have no hope, I have loved ſtrangers, and after them I will go; but remember this, that as great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as thou have attained to this Faith, and are now in glory with the Lord; but on the other hand, let not preſumption ceiſe your heart; for of theſe two ſnares of the Devil, I may juſtly ſay what was ſaid of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Saul hath ſlain his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and David his ten thouſands,</hi> ſo I may likewiſe ſay, that diſpair hath ſlain his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, but preſumption hath ten thouſands: oh my Friends, take heed of preſumptions, prô<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtination in the great concerns of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſouls; 'tis the preſent time that God
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47061:21"/>calls for, 'tis to day, <hi>if you will hear his voyce harden not your heart,</hi> Pſal 95. <hi>acquaint now thy ſelf with him, and be at peace thereby, good ſhall come unto thee,</hi> Job. 22.21. you that are in the prime ſtrength and flower of your years, forget not that <hi>momento,</hi> to <hi>remember thy Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator in the days of thy Youth,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1. <hi>Agree with thine Adverſary quickly whilſt thou art in the way with him,</hi> Mat. 5.25. <hi>Now is the accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed time, and now is the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.3. On poor ſoul, whilſt thou flattereſt thy ſelf with future Repentance, thou wouldeſt do well to conſider both the ſhortneſs and uncertainty of thy life, thou mayſt reſolve to repent tomorrow, and before tomorrow thou mayſt be in Hell; therefore poor ſoul, I do beſeech thee, as if God did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee by me, ſlip no preſent opportunity of thy hearing the word preached, where it is preached in the power and purity of it; for there mayſt thou expect the preſence of God with it and his bleſſing upon it; and though thou ſhouldeſt come there with the Devil of unbelief in thy heart, thou knoweſt not but there God may caſt him out, and if it ſhall be thus with thee in thy waiting on Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that there ſhall be any ſtirrings on thy heart, and the word fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home upon thee.</p>
            <p>Take heed the pleaſures, or cares of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47061:22"/>world do not choak it, but follow home with ſerious meditation, and beg of God to confirm it with his power; and thou knoweſt not how ſoon God may be pleaſed to ſet it home with ſuch power as may make thee cry out, <hi>what ſhall I do to be ſaved;</hi> and though the work may be ſomwhat ſtrange to thy corrupt nature, yet if God be pleaſed to undertake the work, it ſhall prevail, and then what reaſon haſt thou poor ſoul to bleſs the Lord for his unſpeakable mercy to thee-wards, to bring thee from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto light, from the power of Sathan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it will not be long e're thou ſhalt be for ever adoreing the riches of Gods free grace towards thee in Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father, the higheſt and ultimate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Faith, and the holy ſpirit, be all honour, and glory, and praiſe, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:47061:22"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 29. line 18. <hi>for he'l ſuffer, read he have ſuffered,</hi> p. 48. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 10. <hi>for make the ears thin and empty, r. make thin the ears of thy holy Converſation:</hi> p. 11. l. 4, &amp; 5. <hi>are miſplaced:</hi> p. 111. l. 19. <hi>for living, read loving,</hi> l. 20. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> l. 21. l. 21. <hi>for</hi> Lamaſebachthani, <hi>read</hi> Lama-gnazabtanie, p. 13. l. 12. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>read</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> l. 21. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>read</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
